[reporter 1] Two people have been
found dead at a motel in Sinaloa.
[reporter 2] Last night, forces clashed
as a military operation
confronted cartel members.
[indistinct overlapping voices]
[reporter 3] Police have successfully
captured and arrested
three local cartel members,
all suspected to have been involved…
[reporter 4] …of the crimes
attributed to Iván Gastélum,
who might better be known
as his alias, El Cholo.
[reporter 5] …deployed the military
all across the country.
The deployment signals…
[reporter 6] A tribute was held
to honor all of the brave men and women
who have lost their lives
in the line of duty.
[reporter 7] We will always
remember their sacrifices.
[reporter 8] The military seek to strike
a devastating blow to the cartel
with the loss of one of their leaders.
[man] I know it's about to be a bloodbath.
[upbeat music playing]
[ominous music playing]
BASED ON AN ARTICLE BY
HÉCTOR DE MAULEÓN
[cop 1] Requesting any additional units
in the area.
-[cop 2] Unit Two, en route.
-[cop 3] Unit Six, en route.
[indistinct Spanish dialogue]
Put both hands on the table right now!
Hey. Don't be an idiot.
[echoing] Don't be an idiot.
[indistinct Spanish dialogue]
[gunshot]
[breathes heavily]
FACING EL CHAPO
BASED ON TRUE EVENTS
JANUARY 6TH, 2016 7:00 AM
LOS MOCHIS, SINALOA
[man sighs]
[girl] Stop it!
[giggles]
Elízabeth!
Elízabeth! Don't ignore me
when I talk to you.
Stop it now, okay?
-Here's your uniform and coffee, honey.
-You're the best. Thanks.
How come you don't buy them
more appropriate toys?
Like Barneys or Barbies.
I would never buy them
those ridiculous toys.
It's from Carlitos, Papa.
Course it was. Give me a break.
Hey! Enough!
Will you stop shooting and sit?!
[woman 1] Listen to your dad.
-Eat all your eggs and beans, okay?
-When are you going to buy us a computer?
Mom said we might actually quiet down
because it would keep us busy.
[man] Jeez.
-Do you want me to take this one?
-[sighs]
You remember everything, Joana?
And what did I tell you?
That your papa will buy you a computer
as soon as he can.
Let me ask you two something.
Do you guys think you deserve a computer?
You keep bothering your sister.
And you, have you done your homework?
[Elízabeth] Yes!
-[man] What do you mean, "yes"?
-Well, no.
-[giggles]
-[man] Mm. [chuckles]
But, Dad, I get good grades
and I never ask for anything.
-[man] Well--
-Morning!
Okay, I'll think about it.
-Come on in. Do you want a coffee, or--
-We don't have time. We're late!
Okay, come on, girls.
This is what you get,
'cause you guys kept fooling around
and ran out of time!
-[man] Listen to your mom.
-See you later, Arturo.
[woman 2] Let's go! Run, run, run!
[woman 1] Sorry, sweetie.
May God be with you.
-[woman 2] We're blessed! We have to go.
-[woman 1] Bye.
-[woman 2] Bye!
-Thanks for helping us out.
[sighs]
Hey, Liz is a little troublemaker, huh?
We need to watch what we say
because she's getting clever.
-Yeah, I know.
-Mm-hmm.
Come eat. Aren't you hungry?
No appetite.
Are you feeling okay?
No. To be honest, I haven't been great.
What's wrong, honey?
Is it your head? Your stomach?
What's bothering you?
[woman] I'm pregnant.
I'm pregnant, Arturo.
[somber music sting]
-You're not joking, are you?
-And why would I joke about this?
Another daughter?
Or maybe a son?
[Arturo] Holy shit.
I thought you were taking the pill.
Of course I was, Arturo.
I just forgot a couple of days.
That's all.
[uneasy music playing]
I looked at our budget again,
and with my salary, we should be fine.
We're paying for the house, though.
We're paying for the car.
Not to mention all the girls' needs.
Sweetheart, we're barely staying afloat.
-I just--
-Well…
We won't keep it if it's too much trouble.
[sighs] But that's not
what I want us to do.
I just want to be on the same page,
'cause we're having the baby.
I'll go to Valladares
and ask for the night shift.
Not the night shift, Arturo.
It's way more dangerous, honey.
Then what the hell do I do?
Yes, the night shift will be a bitch,
but I'll get used to it.
But what we can't get used to
is not eating.
Well, I'd rather be poor than a widow. Hm?
[sighs] Oh, sweetheart.
[knocking on door]
[music fades]
Good morning, sir.
Do you have two minutes?
Close the door behind you.
Everything good?
Would it be possible for me
to move over to the night shift?
No can do.
I need you out there during the day.
It's just, well, because you can make more
on the night shift, and, um…
Well, I'm going to be a dad again,
and you know
the expenses that come with that.
You guys are pregnant?
Yeah.
[woman] Hey, what's up, girl?
I just picked up
the baby clothes from Vicky.
Are you okay?
Yeah, don't worry. I'm fine.
I can hold onto these
if you haven't told your husband yet.
I broke the news today.
And how'd it go?
Well, he told me
we'll figure something out.
He wants the night shift, but
it's been dangerous lately, you know?
FEDERAL POLICE
[Valladares] Carmona.
[Arturo] Yes, Commissioner.
I've just been told we're having
an officer transfer from Arteaga.
-Nuevo León?
-Michoacán.
-It's been a little crazy over there, no?
-So you heard that too.
His last name is Rosales.
I put him on the night shift
and I wasn't sure
which patrol to assign him to, but now…
[chuckles]
-Timing worked out perfectly, didn't it?
-Sure.
That baby must be
a lucky charm for you, Arturo.
Well, I'll need it. [chuckles]
Hey, listen, Arturo.
Make sure you watch this guy closely.
We don't know what he's like.
Of course. I'll keep an eye on him.
Good. Okay. I hope you're ready
for your double shift tonight.
-Thanks again.
-[Valladares] Sure.
[man] So, do you like to ride
with a saddle or bareback?
[woman] I hate saddles.
-[man] Ha. So, bareback?
-[woman] Yes.
[man chuckles] Me too.
-[woman] Here you go.
-[man] Thank you.
-[woman] See you next time.
-[man] Thanks, Sandra!
-[woman] Andrea.
-[man] Oh, right, Andrea!
[man chuckles]
[pop song playing on radio]
Wait, I have to go now. Bye.
Only way to get through a shift
is strong-ass coffee.
[Arturo] Hm.
We got a long night of driving around
and sitting on our asses. [chuckles]
Is that all you think we do here?
Chill out. Jesus.
-Look, I'm just trying to fit in.
-Hmm.
So, this coffee's strong to you?
Come on. We just got started.
[police radio] …after forensics,
report to Unit 1 to get…
Well, welcome to Mochis.
[Arturo clears throat]
There you go.
[siren wails]
[uneasy music playing]
[music fades]
[Rosales] Check it out.
[Arturo] He's fucked if he's not careful.
[Rosales] Nah. He has
everything under control.
-[car door opens]
-No, hey, wait!
Man, what the fuck?
Good evening.
[man] Evening.
-[Rosales] Everything in order?
-[man] Of course, Officer.
We're done here. Take these guys away.
Get 'em in the truck.
How's it going, Officer? Need any help?
Oh, no, we'll be okay.
As you can see, I've got it under control.
-Excuse me.
-[man] Hurry up.
[tense music playing]
All right, on your feet.
[Rosales] All right, asshole,
show me some ID.
-We just got here from Tijuana yesterday.
-Yeah, this pendejo.
MUNICIPAL POLICE
Hey, I'm keeping my eye on you.
[man] All right,
let's get the fuck out of here.
I'm guessing you've already started
logging the evidence, right?
Standard practice, Officer.
-Hey, don't do--
-Don't do what?
Know your place.
That's a lot of coke.
Just say the word and we'd be happy
to provide an escort to the DA.
Or actually, I should probably
just call in the seizure now.
Okay, Officer.
Let's go to Ahome.
Come on.
Hey!
[Arturo] Can I help you, gentlemen?
Is there a problem?
I'm cool.
Then move along.
[engine revs]
Lead the way.
Come on, let's go! Let's move out!
[Arturo sighs]
[Rosales exhales]
[Arturo exhales]
[radio beeps]
Dispatch, do you read?
-Carmona…
-This is dispatch.
Do you realize
you just screwed with that officer's deal?
[music fades]
[lively music playing]
All right. Thanks, Erick.
[woman] I'll be waiting for you
at the motel, okay, baby?
Save some energy for me.
[disconnect tone]
Here you go.
This is supposed to be good?
Hm. It's the best in Mochis.
Hey, Rosales.
What was all that at the gas station?
[tense music playing]
I'm sorry, what?
What were you showing those assholes
on your phone?
I'm a little confused
about how you do things.
What the hell?
Look, asshole, I don't have to explain
how I work to you.
What's your problem?
I don't have a problem.
-[spits]
-[coffee splashes]
What a fucking prick.
[music fades]
[wife] Arturo?
[Arturo] Yeah.
Morning, honey.
-[Arturo] Hey, good morning.
-I missed you.
Want some breakfast? Are you hungry?
I'm exhausted more than anything,
so I'll just eat whatever you have.
There's machaca. And of course
you're tired. How could you not be?
[Arturo exhales]
Wow, this is good. Who drew it?
Joana. You know, the artist in the family.
-[Arturo] She's pretty good.
-Here, have some juice too.
[Arturo] Thank you.
Okay, so how was it?
How'd it go with your new partner?
What's he like?
Well, I can't really figure out who he is.
Why? What happened?
I think it's first day-nerves
or something.
[wife] Hm.
How are you doing?
Fine.
Um…
Well, actually, I've been thinking
about what you said.
-And I think that maybe--
-Wait.
-I was just--
-[Arturo] I'm sorry.
-[somber music playing]
-To be honest, I was caught off guard.
[inhales]
But one more kid isn't that different,
so I'm sure we'll be okay.
You sure?
[tense music playing]
Completely sure.
[bystanders scream]
[gunshot]
[gulps]
[groans]
[sighs]
[exhales]
Honey, are you okay?
What time is it?
It's a little after seven o'clock.
Your partner was early,
so I let him inside. He's on the couch.
Rosales?
[door opens]
[wife] Hey, girls?
-You girls do your homework?
-[both] Yes, Papa.
Wow, I'm proud of both of you.
Now go to your rooms
and get ready for bed. Come on.
-Nice to meet you. And be careful tonight.
-Have a good night.
-[wife] I got it.
-Thanks.
[wife] Come on, girls. Brush your teeth.
Why are you so early?
I, uh… I, uh, got you a peace offering.
Give me ten. I'll be right out.
[Rosales] You have a beautiful family.
[tense music playing]
You know, when I got assigned
to work with you,
you sounded familiar.
But I really couldn't figure out
from where though.
And then it finally hit me.
Of course.
He's Agent Carmona.
Everyone's heard of your case.
At least you made it out alive
though, right?
Do you know what keeps me up
every fucking night?
Those murdered kids.
I keep thinking of my daughters,
and it fucks with me,
because maybe if I had
just gotten there a little earlier…
I'm fucked up.
You can't keep blaming yourself, cabrón.
It's a miracle he didn't kill you.
Yeah.
How come you wear
such a nice watch to work?
You know a lot about watches?
I know enough.
Because you don't know shit about coffee.
[Arturo chuckles]
[music fades]
[man 1] Commander.
[unsettling music playing]
You there, Bravo?
[man 2] Go ahead, Alpha.
Can you confirm
how many civilians are present?
[man 2] Our cameras
recorded three civilians yesterday,
and no one has left or entered since,
so confirming three.
[man 3] Oh, shit.
Seems like a lot of tacos
for two thugs, right?
Yeah. That's a whole taqueria.
[music fades]
[unsettling music resumes]
Puta madre. [clears throat]
They're armed.
[man 3] Looks like they're the ones
who ordered the tacos, Foco.
-Is El Cholo there?
-[Foco] I'm not sure.
[man 3] Listen, Foco,
if El Cholo's inside,
things are gonna get pretty crazy.
But I won't let us die today.
NAVY
[music fades]
[tense music playing]
-[man 4] Unit 10, go ahead.
-[man 5] Moving in now.
[music fades]
[dramatic music playing]
-Fuck, it's the feds!
-[man 6] Get this shit out of here!
-[man 7] They're already inside!
-[man 3] All right, boys, let's move!
Move it! Come on.
Get in position!
Stand clear. Breach the door!
[gunfire]
Let's go! Push forward!
-Get him out of here!
-Help the corporal!
-[Foco] It's okay, man. I got you.
-[corporal] My arm!
[corporal groans]
[man 3] You'll be okay. Hold on.
Deploy grenade!
Weapons hot!
Ready? Let's fucking move!
Keep pressing forward!
Go, go, go!
Clear that room! Check the columns!
Move forward, Foco. Cover the stairs.
Any asshole that tries to run gets shot.
Okay, Foco. Vamos. Advance.
Keep going, Foco!
-[Foco] Come on, boys. Stairway is clear!
-[man 3] Make sure to check that room.
[Foco] Don't fucking move!
Get on the ground!
-[man 2] Hands on the floor!
-[man 8] Don't move!
Keep your fucking hands
where I can see them!
Where the fuck is he? Where's El Cholo?
Fucking talk, cabrón!
[man 3] See if El Cholo's
in the other room!
-[man 2] Stay on the ground!
-[man 3] Take point, Foco!
-On it.
-[man 3] Secure the room!
Put your fucking hands up, cabrón!
On the floor!
Where are you going, cabrón?
Get back down. Come down!
That's right, asshole. Against the wall!
Where did he go?
-What?
-[man 3] Where did El Cholo go?
-I have no idea, I swear!
-Where the fuck is he? Don't lie to me!
[woman] I came with him.
-[man 3] Hey, Cortez!
-[Cortez] Yes, sir!
[man 3] Come here. Secure this area.
[Cortez] Yes, sir!
Don't move. Don't fucking move!
Just like that, asshole!
-[man 2] Hurry up!
-Check everywhere!
Check the closet,
the furniture. Everything!
-[Cortez] Yes, sir!
-Rip this place apart.
He couldn't have fucking vanished.
I know he's here somewhere.
-[panting]
-[tense music playing]
[man 9] It smells like shit.
Damn it, Cholo!
[El Cholo] Just a little further, boss.
[boss] I'm sick
of all these fucking tunnels.
[El Cholo] Suck it up, boss.
You've been through way fucking worse.
[man 1] Vice Admiral, in here.
[music fades]
[vice admiral] What did you find?
[man 1] Thought this might be something.
Check it out.
Everybody, be quiet.
[boss] This is bullshit!
I'm sick of running around
like a fucking rat
through these goddamn tunnels!
[hollow knocking]
[vice admiral] Okay. Get ready, men!
[tense music playing]
-Let's go!
-[Cortez] There's a tunnel, sir!
Sweep the tunnel. See how far it goes.
Damn it. These pendejos
and their fucking tunnels. Come on.
Goddamn it. Corporal?
Tell the admiral we're gonna be
needing more aerial support ASAP.
-[man 10] Copy that, sir.
-Get on it!
Any news?
Unit 2 has just returned. They had
to turn back because of the water level.
-We think it leads to the sewage system.
-Puta madre.
If El Cholo hasn't drowned already,
he'll come out of a manhole.
-Foco.
-Commander.
Get everyone ready. We're leaving.
But leave one unit here just in case.
Yes, sir.
Lieutenant, have the air unit report to us
with anything suspicious.
-Let's clear out, gentlemen!
-[men] Yes, sir.
[man 2] Let's go, marines!
[music stops]
[helicopter blades whirring]
Who is that? Army or the marines?
Not sure.
I just wanna get through this shift
'cause I'm getting some tonight.
Don't you mean this morning?
[siren wails]
-Morning.
-[Valladares] Morning, boys.
Did you see the helicopters?
We heard them flying over us,
but what are they doing right now?
The Navy was just involved in a clash,
but they haven't told us who it was with.
And they asked us to make sure
all of our units stand by
and hold their positions.
Copy that.
So stay here
and keep watching the freeway.
-Okay?
-We'll keep a lookout, sir.
-[car door closes]
-[engine starts]
Adios!
This shit just keeps getting worse
[scoffs]
Looks like you might not get some at all.
Shut up, Carmona!
You should probably just cancel
with the lucky girl now.
Or lucky guy. I don't judge.
Yeah, you wish, cabrón.
I have a whole roster of girls, you know?
-[lively music plays on radio]
-Chinga su madre!
[in Spanish] ♪ In Reynosa, Tamaulipas ♪
♪ Men are determined ♪
♪ That's why we remember them ♪
♪ By singing their ballads ♪
♪ There in Zacatecas, they killed ♪
♪ A federal highway agent ♪
[in English] Could you be more basic with
your fucking choice in music, Carmona?
"El Federal de Caminos," really?
What the fuck do you listen to?
I listen to real music, cabrón!
-Los Ángeles Negros, for example.
-[laughs]
[boss] Where the fuck are we?
-[El Cholo] Just a little further.
-[boss] Cholo, goddamn it.
["El Federal de Caminos"
continues on radio]
-Hey, Carmona.
-What?
Does this area get pretty hot?
Well, like anywhere,
it can get a little hot.
Usually, it's normal.
Right now, it's calm.
You
been paid off ever?
Not me, no.
[tense music playing]
[strains]
[boss groans]
[horn honks]
-[boss] Stop the car.
-[El Cholo] Pull over!
[boss] Get out of the fucking car.
Hurry up. Get out!
-Out of the car!
-[woman] Okay.
-[boss] Shut up!
-[woman] Okay. Please, I'm getting out.
[El Cholo] We don't have all day!
-[woman] We have to go.
-[boss] Let's go!
[tires squeal]
-Are you okay?
-We're okay. He's gone.
Oh God.
[child cries]
-We're okay, sweetheart.
-It's over now.
[tense music playing]
Where's the ambulance?
[man 1] Dispatch, do you read?
We've cleared the building.
No snipers confirmed.
-You doing okay?
-[man 1] 87-7.
[woman] Be advised. A 56-21 has
been reported on Guillermo Prieto Street.
A 2005 red Ford Focus,
plate Victor, Kilo, Whiskey,
two, zero, six.
I repeat, plates Victor, Kilo, Whiskey,
Come on, we've been on the clock
for 12 hours now.
[radio beeps]
-Don't whine.
-[man 2] Unit 3, checking in.
Overtime's always nice.
I don't need extra cash.
I just wanna go get laid.
[man 3] Yeah, I was told to stay here
on Main and Third.
[tense music playing]
Hey. Isn't that the car that was stolen?
Looks like it.
Unit 18, beginning pursuit.
[siren wails]
I've got a 55 with a 56, a possible 21.
Pull over to the right
and stop your vehicle immediately.
[tires squeal]
Out of the car!
[El Cholo] Fucking pigs.
[boss] Easy. Relax, Cholo.
What the fuck are you trying to do to us,
cabrónes? What's your commander's name?
-The boss is with me, pendejo!
-Drop your weapons now!
[scoffs]
Maybe your lucky day. Don't dick around.
We gotta get out of here.
-That's enough!
-Drop your weapons now!
Take two steps back.
I said two steps back!
Hey, hands up. Come on!
Put those on.
Happy, cabrón?
[Rosales] Come here.
That's it. Don't move.
Do you know who I am?
Uh, yeah, I do.
Now please step out of the vehicle.
Calm down, man. Let's fix this.
We need you to take us to Che Ríos.
Not another word.
Turn around!
Come with me to the patrol car.
Come on.
You too.
Andale, cabrón! Move it!
Walk.
Get in.
Come on, get in.
Carmona.
[man on radio] Unit 20 reporting in.
We're back on patrol now. Over.
-[El Cholo] Taking a photo?
-Shut your mouth!
[El Cholo] Fuck you, pig!
-I have to cuff you. It's protocol.
-[boss] Fucking bullshit.
[car door closes]
Fuck.
[cell phone dialing]
[cell phone beeping]
Goddamn it.
What are you doing, cabrón?
Why'd you take that photo?
If you get caught with this,
we'll be shit out of luck.
-Whose fucking side are you on?
-The side where I live, cabrón!
Fuck, just let me think.
Just let me think!
What happened last time
you stuck to protocol?
Innocent people were gunned down.
How dare you say that shit to me?
That fucking photo might save our lives.
Yours and mine, asshole.
It's El Chapo Guzmán, cabrón!
You know what I think?
We should do nothing,
and let 'em drive away.
Carmona…
I don't wanna die today.
And I think you feel the same.
Let's fucking live.
They've already seen our faces.
And they've seen our patrol car number.
We let them go and we're fucked.
And if we take them to where they want…
We'll be fucked either way then.
Well, we can't stay here.
If we don't leave soon,
his men will find us and kill us.
-Carmona…
-Yeah?
We're already dead, cabrón.
Not even God
can protect us.
We'll protect each other, cabrón.
[music fades]
[sighs]
[tense music playing]
[man 1] Hey, let's go!
What are you lazy fucks
even doing right now?
Listen up! Put that shit out, dumbass.
They tried to take down the boss,
but he was able to escape. Huh?
The fuck are you waiting for?
We gotta find him before the marines do.
[men] Yes, sir!
-All right, vamonos.
-[man 2] Hey, let's go!
-[man 3] Hurry!
-[man 4] Move!
-[man 5] Fucking go! Come on!
-[man 2] In the fucking car!
[man 6] Let's get him.
[music fades]
ARTURO, WHERE ARE YOU? CALL ME, PLEASE
[cell phone buzzes]
Hey, officers. We've wasted
a lot of time, you know?
Let's stop fucking around.
Step on the gas
and I'll tell you where to go.
Cooperate, assholes!
Hey, Cholo!
Fuck you, cabrón!
Puta madre.
[vehicle approaching]
[radio beeps]
Hey, guys? I've got some cops here.
P-F-14-82.
-[man on radio] Anyone with them?
-Yeah. A combo.
[tense music playing]
Fuck me.
Oh shit.
Hey, officers.
Our lookout already saw you.
-This is fucking crazy.
-[El Cholo] But it's not too late.
All you have to do is help me
get the boss to Che Ríos.
Help me deliver him safely, and I promise
your life will completely change.
Come on, cabrónes!
Yeah, they've got the boss in the back.
The boss can give you
as much as you want, okay?
Stop dicking around,
and just say a fucking number!
Come on, pendejos!
Ten million!
For each of you, eh?
Come on, Commander.
No way, man. Come on.
There's no fucking way.
Don't do it.
[gunshots]
-Is he down? Looks like he's down.
-Yeah, he's down.
Puta madre!
-Don't make me repeat myself.
-Come on and take it, pendejos!
I'm gonna remember how many you kill.
[music fades]
You guys never answered.
This is gonna be my final offer.
Fifteen million for each of you.
Think carefully
because a shitload of people
are going to die.
The people who failed
to warn me quickly enough,
the people who didn't shut down
those fucking marines,
and the people who think
they can bring me in like a trophy.
Are you one of those people?
[ominous music playing]
That's up to you.
[inaudible dialogue]
You're going into Las Canteras?
[music fades]
Come in, Magas!
[man] Why are we stopping?
Ah, it's Magas.
What's wrong?
Piojo just called me, sir.
Those cops took out Sky and Hormiga.
What's the move?
-They were the ones on Highway 32?
-[Magas] Yes, boss.
[sighs]
What the hell?
Let's keep going.
[tense music playing]
The fuck do these assholes want?
They really following us?
Ha! Looks like the cavalry's here.
You fucked up for sure. Big time.
Well, you're in the crossfire.
And if they shoot, you're not the ones
with the bulletproof vests.
Better not move, assholes.
[music fades]
Hi.
What the fuck do we do now?
We can't let them get close to the car
or we're seriously fucked.
I have to piss.
No, wait, wait, come on.
You have to be fucking kidding me, cabrón.
Divide and conquer.
Don't let 'em get close.
[tense music playing]
Morning, Commander.
You seem lost.
We'll just fill up and go, okay?
These cops are fucking idiots.
They don't know what they're doing.
-Yeah.
-Gonna get killed.
[whispers] Chinga su madre.
Could you both put away your guns
and show me your permits?
It's just protocol.
You're a funny guy.
[breathes deeply]
We all good here?
Don't be stupid.
Let go.
There we go.
Nice and easy.
[Arturo] Relax, buddy,
unless you wanna set off some fireworks.
What happened?
Why all the violence?
Huh? We're just getting our gas.
We don't want any problems.
Hurry up and leave while you still can.
Good.
Nothing's gonna happen, huh?
-What do I owe you for the gas?
-You don't owe me anything, Officer.
[Rosales] Right.
[music fades]
So, what then? We can take 'em one on one.
If we keep driving in circles
with those cabrónes,
we'll end up dead.
[cell phone dialing]
What are you doing?
Pick up the fucking phone, Valladares.
I'm sending the photo.
Are you sure?
[tense music playing]
What about hiding at Motel del Puerto?
It's close by.
Heh?
Sounds good. All right.
[engine starts]
[music fades]
-You like that?
-[woman] Yeah, it feels so good.
[woman breathes heavily]
What? Did you come?
I can't believe your motel's
gonna help us get out of this mess.
God protects the horny, Carmona.
There has to be a shit ton of lookouts
by now, so we have to stay alert.
[Rosales] Right.
Book a room for us.
I'll move the patrol car to the back
so it's out of view.
You take El Chapo. I'll take El Cholo.
Divide and conquer?
Okay.
Carmona.
The thing with the phone back then?
It's because he asked for the address
of where they were taking his friend.
And since I didn't know,
I looked it up and showed him.
And my watch?
It was a gift from my old man.
On his death bed.
Rosales,
I know who you are.
[upbeat music playing on radio]
-Morning.
-Morning! Um, how can I help?
-[Arturo] How many rooms do you have?
-How many do you need?
We have 60 rooms.
One's all we need.
[music stops]
[car door closes]
Come on, man. Let's strike a deal
now that your partner's inside.
Deliver me to Che Ríos.
It's just one small thing you have to do,
and then you'll be set
for the rest of your life.
Imagine how nice it'll be
to never worry about money again.
And you know what's even better than that?
Your entire family,
including you,
will enter my protection.
I promise.
No one will touch you.
So come on, let's go.
[El Cholo] Take the deal, Officer.
That's the best fucking decision
you'll ever make in your life, cabrón.
I don't know if I can.
Don't think about it. Just start driving.
We got a deal, man.
Hurry up, we're in a rush.
Let's get the fuck out of here, cabrón.
How many are taken?
-[upbeat music playing on radio]
-Only three.
That one, right on the corner.
Number 51.
-It's available?
-[woman] Yeah.
350 pesos for three hours.
[music stops]
Know how long I've been with the police?
Twenty-nine years.
And in my career,
I have seen a whole lot of bullshit.
Especially shit that assholes like you do.
I retire next year.
I've been thinking, you know,
what better gift
than to see you two get what you deserve,
to rot away in a cell?
I'm gonna fucking--
[tense music playing]
[El Chapo] That's enough. Relax, Cholo.
-I'm gonna fucking kill you.
-[Rosales] Sit the fuck down, asshole.
Don't worry.
He'll get his soon.
-[growls softly]
-[knocking on window]
[engine starts]
What do you think
those guys are doing here?
[man] How the fuck should I know?
Puta madre.
[woman] Maybe they're here
to blow off some steam too.
Shh!
Hold on.
-Can you please just spit out a number?
-Okay, come on.
-[El Cholo] Wait, what?
-Get out.
Hey! Where the fuck
are you taking the boss, cabrón?
[man] Holy shit!
There's no fucking way.
[camera clicks]
I can't believe it.
What the fuck?
That asshole kinda looks like…
Like who?
Keep going.
[El Cholo] Put away your fucking gun.
Let's fight like men, motherfucker!
Where the hell's he taking him, cabrón?
[key jangles]
[music fades]
[Arturo] Get in.
Sit down.
[cell phone buzzing and ringing]
INCOMING CALL
ISA
Shit.
-Keep it up, you guys. Good work.
-[man] Yes, sir.
[cell phone buzzes]
[cell phone buzzes and rings]
Now you fucking call me.
Give me a sec.
Morning.
Cut the shit, Carmona.
Who the fuck sent you that photo?
No one did, sir.
I took the photo.
[scoffs]
No way. Where are you?
Well, since you didn't answer,
we had no choice but to lay low
and hide out with him at a motel.
You mean… You mean…
You mean to tell me this is real?
Su puta madre!
I'll send out the photo right away.
Wait! We have to think this through
before we send it.
[Valladares] You're right.
Who can we trust?
I know. Everybody'll get the photo.
My supervisors, the Navy, the Army.
I'll send it to everyone!
Stay right where you are.
Listen to me. Stay put.
And don't talk to anyone, okay?
Every road will be crawling with
those thugs, looking for that bastard.
All right, but you better hurry up
and get here,
because having to stay
with this motherfucker
is like babysitting the devil.
[Valladares] I can only imagine.
Just hang in there, okay? Don't leave
the room, and don't talk to him.
[El Chapo] What's your plan?
[music stops]
I'm not gonna try to run, so can you
please just, uh, take these off me?
[sighs]
Commander, there's something
I wanna ask you.
You and I have nothing to talk about, so
I'm going to ask you
to just stay quiet, please.
[cell phone ringing]
How come you didn't reply to me?
Did you see the fucking photo?
[tense music playing]
Yes, you idiot. It's El Chapo!
Okay, okay, I got it.
Listen, baby, you have to let me know
if any more cops show up,
or take him away.
-Okay.
-[man 1] Thanks.
Hurry the hell up and get us
to Motel del Puerto. The boss is there!
Everyone, fucking head over
to Motel del Puerto.
Motel del Puerto, hurry.
[man 1] I'm about to send you a photo.
Find out who the fuck this is.
I'LL CALL U RIGHT BACK
[man 2] His name is Arturo Carmona,
and he lives in Ahome, Sinaloa.
He's happily married with two kids.
All right, man.
I'll hit you up later, cabrón.
[cell phone dialing]
Guatafuck.
I'm about to send over an address.
A fucking cop lives there, okay?
He has a wife and a couple of kids.
Call me when it's done, eh?
[music fades]
Good morning, Rosita.
Yeah, it's… it's Isaura.
Look, I'm a little worried
because Arturo's shift ended a while ago,
and he hasn't gotten home yet
and won't answer my calls.
[exhales]
[sniffs]
[telephone ringing]
Yeah, what is it?
Put her through.
This is Commissioner Valladares.
How can I help?
M… M… Morning, sir.
This is Isaura. I'm looking for Arturo.
Know where he is?
Arturo is, uh, on special operations
so he'll be late getting home.
Listen, you need to pick up your daughters
from school now and take 'em home.
But is Arturo gonna be okay?
And what do you mean by operation?
[Valladares] Isaura, please,
take the girls home
and wait for Arturo to get there.
If anything goes wrong, call me.
Oh my God.
-Okay.
-[bell rings]
Stay right here.
I'll find out what's going on.
[cell phone buzzing and ringing]
[chuckles softly]
You wife must be worried about you, right?
I'm not in the mood to play your games,
so let's just sit here in silence, okay?
I don't understand what makes you think
that you'll be rewarded
for bringing me in.
Huh?
I already told you.
I got everyone in your whole department
in my goddamn pocket, hombre!
[tense music playing]
When will you stop playing dumb, Officer?
You clearly care a lot
about your family, Carmona.
And you'd probably
do anything for them, no?
-[music fades]
-Everything I do, I do for my children.
Now it's your turn.
You need to do
what you need to do for them.
If you don't accept the offer
I'm willing to give you, my friend,
then someone else will, cabrón.
So it might as well be you.
So let's do it, Officer.
[inhales]
Mm. [mutters]
Officer, can you pass me
a bottle of water?
I'm… I'm really thirsty.
It's just a bottle of water,
for fuck's sake.
[tense music playing]
Don't be an idiot.
You think you're slick?
[music fades]
No. I just wanted to ask you
to open it for me.
Come on, help me out.
Pretty please?
[gun clicks]
[suspenseful music playing]
[music fades]
-[door handle rattles]
-[Arturo] Hey, hey.
Stay there.
[door handle rattles]
-[door handle rattles]
-[tense music playing]
[breathes shakily]
[El Chapo] You're scared
to death, aren't you?
So this is your first time
being in deep shit like this.
Chingada madre!
[music fades]
[Foco] We have units
in these three sectors.
This is where we are.
Thanks to the information
from the sewer company,
every drain is covered now.
[marine] Understood.
[vice admiral sighs]
Puta madre.
What if this fucker slipped away?
He should have
come out of a storm drain by now.
[cell phone chimes]
[suspenseful music playing]
[cell phone rings]
Go ahead, Admiral.
[music fades]
Understood.
[suspenseful music resumes]
-Foco!
-Sir.
The Federal Police have El Cholo.
And look at the prize they got.
It's El Chapo, Commander.
Venado!
Get us the address of Motel del Puerto.
That's where the party's at.
-[Venado] Yes, sir.
-Let's move, everyone! To the motel!
Let's go, marines!
[engine starts]
[music stops]
-[breathing shakily]
-[tense music playing]
[Isaura] Gracias.
-[teacher] May God be with you.
-Thank you.
Hurry up. Get in, get in.
[man 1] Boss! We got heat Incoming.
[man 2] Chingada madre.
-Commander?
-What do you got?
Seems like those assholes
might know where to go too.
Think you're right, Foco.
Hey, boys, you guys
can take care of those marines.
We'll go on ahead to the motel.
[vice admiral] Captain,
however this goes down,
just keep following
anybody who tries to escape.
[tires squeal]
-Split off and chase them down.
-[marine] Yes, sir!
[vice admiral] Don't let them get away!
Step on it, Foco!
Don't lose them, marine. Come on!
We have to catch up to those assholes!
[tires squeal]
[music fades]
Let's dance, cabrónes!
[man 1] Come on, let's go!
[man 2] We're going to fuck you up!
[Magas] Bring it on!
-[Venado] Put the guns down now!
-You first, cabrón!
[Venado] Put them down now!
Hold your ground, cabrónes!
[Venado] Surrender now!
Don't make me fucking say it again.
Everyone, put down your weapons now!
There's nowhere to run.
[man 3] Fuck this!
[man 3 grunts]
Okay, okay!
[Venado] Move in.
Stay alert.
-On the ground!
-[marine 1] Put your hands on the floor!
-[marine 2] Show me your hands!
-[marine 3] Don't fucking try anything.
[Venado] That's it, motherfucker.
Keep your hands on your head.
Uh, h… how are you doing, girls?
What… What did you
take us out of school for, Mama?
[tense music playing]
Come on.
Come here.
Go on. Run. Hurry. Come on, let's go.
Get inside the house. I'll be right there.
[music fades]
[both breathing anxiously]
I didn't get to finish my lunch, Mama.
I'm still hungry!
Oh, sweetie.
Listen, girls, I need you
to go to your rooms
and eat the rest of your lunch there.
After that, pick out your favorite toy,
and, um, I'll be there soon
to join you, okay?
[Isaura chuckles softly]
Go have fun.
Love you both.
[El Chapo] Stop being irresponsible.
Think about the future of your kids.
Do you know how many kids
I have? Fucking 18.
And all of those kids
have everything they could ever need.
You know why?
It's because I can. Because of money.
And with that money,
I also provide for the countless kids
who were born with a gun in their hands
instead of a bottle to drink.
There's a shitload of those kids.
Well, I'm not saying that I don't think
you've been a good provider.
But those kids
that you claim to be helping?
They're all just living on their knees.
But they eat because of me.
Right. You feed them.
Then you make them kill.
Then they end up dead.
Ah, chingá!
Don't policemen kill people too?
Pretty much the same
if you think about it.
The only difference
between your men and mine
is that you guys
barely have enough to get by,
and my men can't spend it fast enough.
Huh.
Doesn't sound too bad.
[El Chapo] So, Carmona,
how many people have you killed?
[distant helicopters approaching]
[tense music playing]
Enough, cabrón!
Get me the fuck out of here! Come on!
Can't you just tell me
what the fuck you want, cabrón?!
-Ask for whatever you want, puto!
-[Arturo] Sit down. Fucking sit!
-[El Chapo] Don't be a fucking--
-Sit your ass down!
[El Cholo] Listen, Officer.
I know I'm fucked,
and the boss might be fucked, too,
but don't forget
about how this is gonna play out for you.
I'm gonna murder your entire family,
one by one, in front of you, cabrón.
You really think anyone has your back?
No one's gonna save you.
You're on your own!
Go fuck yourself.
You can put me in a fucking prison,
but once I get in,
I'm gonna put a million on your head.
What makes you think
you'll actually make it there?
Who knows you're here?
It's only me.
And you have no fucking idea
how much I wanna blow your brains out.
So just keep mouthing off, and you'll--
Took you guys long enough.
Where the hell were you?
[man] This is Commander Carmona's
patrol car, right?
[breathes shakily]
[man] Answer me, cabrón!
They were able
to get the boss too! El Chapo!
Rosales?
The fuck are you doing
all the way out here?
Barraza?
Yes, dumbass!
[exhales]
Pinche, Barraza!
Jesus, you scared the shit outta me, man.
So wait, how long you been in Mochis?
[chuckles wryly] Three days, cabrón.
[Barraza chuckles]
-Fuck!
-And you?
Man, it smells
like you haven't showered in weeks.
Shit, that's because I've been undercover.
Well, you guys are fucking precious, yeah?
Enough with the fucking reunion!
What the hell do we do, cabrón?
If his men get here before ours do,
we might as well be dead, guey.
We'll be ready.
-Good luck.
-Yeah.
[helicopter blades whirring]
[suspenseful music playing]
Okay, marine, don't lose him now.
Keep close.
Goddamn it!
We gotta lose those motherfuckers
before we get to the motel.
[man 1] Step on it, man.
They're right on our ass!
Get ready, Foco.
The shitstorm's about to begin.
Fuck it, stop the car, man. Let's just
fucking square up with these marines.
Stick with them. We're close.
-[man 2] Are you sure, boss?
-Stop the damn car.
Okay, sir.
-What's up, assholes? Fucking want some?!
-Take cover!
I swear to God,
I'm gonna kill all you motherfuckers!
-[marine 1] Take cover!
-[Foco] Get down!
Come at me, assholes!
Suck my fucking dick!
-[marine 2 groans]
-I got you. Stay down!
Press forward when they reload!
I'm gonna cut your heads off,
hijos de puta!
-Foco, Vaquero, move in, left flank!
-Sir!
Reload!
Puma, Black Charro! On me!
-Fuck.
-[man 1] Fuck you, pigs!
Counterattack! Go!
[tense music playing]
Fuck you, jarheads!
[vice admiral] Grenade!
[groaning]
[music fades]
You're not gonna get anything
for turning me in, Carmona.
And you'll be fucked if you do.
Come on. You know how it is over there.
The government or the DEA
will make you and your family disappear.
Because then they can blame it on me,
and give me a longer sentence.
'Cause that's what they do.
You know I'm right.
Listen, I'm giving you my word.
Just take me to Che Ríos
and I'll give you ten million.
Fifteen.
You promised 15.
Ah, that was before.
But if we get there today, I promise you,
I'll have my men waiting there
with ten million in cash.
You think you can buy me off?
Not me.
You don't have all of us in your pocket.
You think you're a good person,
like you're a saint, don't you?
I had to kill a kid
who was selling your shit,
and two innocent people died that day.
Because we're at war.
And civilians end up dying as collateral
in the crossfire.
Because of people like you,
who murder and poison society.
I don't understand how someone like you
can even sleep at night.
Seriously.
And you think that if you just keep
building chapels you're forgiven?
Fuck off!
I can't wait to put you away
so I can watch you rot in that cell.
But if I can't put you in jail…
then I'll put you in the ground.
[tense music sting]
[vehicle approaching]
[distant thud]
[tense music playing]
The girls.
[man 1] Come on, move it!
-[gasps]
-[Joana] Is that Papa?
[Elízabeth] What's wrong? Who's outside?
-[Isaura] Come here. Shh.
-[Joana] I'm getting scared, mama.
Don't worry, girls.
Dad will be here soon, I promise.
-Who's outside?
-Shh, shh. Let's lower our voices.
-We're gonna be fine.
-[Elízabeth] I'm scared.
-[Isaura] Shh.
-[Elízabeth] Where is Papa?
TWO TRUCKS FULL OF HITMEN
CAME TO THE HOUSE.
[Isaura] Answer me, Arturo.
THE THREE OF US ARE HERE.
[cell phone chimes]
[tense music playing]
[breathes shakily]
This can't be happening.
[cell phone dialing]
-Where's Papa?
-Arturo!
Isa!
Arturo, there are two trucks outside
and they're--
[screams]
Hey!
No! Please, please, don't shoot!.
You assholes get the fuck out of my house!
-Please, sir, please!
-Who are they, Mama?
Leave them alone!
Sounds like they already made it inside.
[panicked breathing on phone]
[Isaura] Please!
Please don't kill us!
Tell them to stand down.
Tell them to back off!
[Isaura] No! Please, please!
Say it! Tell your guys to let them go!
[vehicle approaching]
[Isaura] Please!
How did you think this was going to end?
[Joana] Mama, I'm scared.
[El Chapo] I told you. This is what
you get for playing the hero, cabrón.
They're my daughters, man.
They're just little kids!
[Isaura] No, don't shoot!
-They're gonna keep screaming for help.
-[Isaura] Please!
And there's nothing you can do.
[suspenseful music playing]
[indistinct clamoring on phone]
-[Isaura] Please!
-Isa!
-[crying on phone]
-Isa, are you there?
-[Isaura] Please!
-[Elízabeth cries]
We didn't do anything.
Are you there?
Shush. Please don't hurt them!
They're just kids, so please don't.
-Can you--
-[gunshot]
[silence]
[breathing shakily]
Now I'm going
to fucking kill you, motherfucker!
[vice admiral] Drop your gun, Officer!
You're fucking dead, puto!
-I need you to calm down, Officer!
-I'm gonna fucking blow your brains out!
Stand down! I'm giving you an order
as the vice admiral!
I swear I'm gonna
fucking blow your brains out!
[marine] Put it down, Officer.
[screams]
[cell phone buzzing and ringing]
[exhales]
[Isaura breathes shakily]
Arturo! We're okay.
[cries]
[haunting music playing]
[gunshot]
[screams] Don't look!
[crying]
The… The Army got to us. We're okay.
[breathing shakily]
Your six-month vacation is over, Chapo.
Yeah.
I'm done.
Piece of shit!
Okay, okay, you got him. Now relax.
Escort him out.
Let me go. Don't touch me.
Marines!
[El Chapo groans quietly]
At this moment, you are at the disposal
of the Mexican Naval Forces.
I got your buddy waiting for you.
That is, if he's still alive.
[marine] Orders, sir?
[vice admiral] Bring him out!
[tense music playing]
[soldier] Mexican Army! Surrender!
Hurry up! Everyone, on the ground!
Hands behind your head.
Give us your weapons!
Come on, hurry up! All of you!
[sirens wail]
-[man 1] Keep that clear.
-[man 2] Two over there, three over here.
We got you guys a present.
Rot in hell.
[man 2] All right, copy that.
-[Valladares] Are you okay?
-I'm fine, sir.
Well done, Carmona.
You've nothing to worry about.
Your family and your house
will be under the protection of the Army.
-Thanks.
-[vice admiral] Hello, gentlemen.
Vice Admiral Ortega.
Officers, thanks for your cooperation.
Commissioner,
get your men out of here
as soon as possible. For your own safety.
From this point on, the Navy
will take these two into their custody.
What are you doing?
[man 1] Stand down!
Stand down. Hold your fire.
-[man 2] Put your fucking guns down!
-[man 1] Hold fire. Stand down.
[man 3] Hold your fire.
-[man 1] Soldier.
-[man 2] Put your guns down!
-[man 1] Relax!
-[man 3] Come on.
It was the Federal Police, not the Navy,
who captured Joaquin Guzmán.
So we're all gonna go together
to the presidential hangar to report it.
Are we clear?
Marines!
[marines] Yes, sir!
Put your weapons down!
Federales, lower your weapons!
[poignant music playing]
-Marines!
-[marines] Yes, sir!
-Escort them out!
[Valladares] Well done, boys.
[helicopter blades whirring]
JANUARY 8, 2016 10:32 AM
LOS MOCHIS, SINALOA
You good?
Yeah, I'm good.
Those marine assholes
were trying to take all of the credit.
Doesn't matter to me
who takes the credit for it.
I just worry about the Army
keeping their word to us.
No, don't say that, Carmona.
They'll protect us.
I'm a year from retirement, man.
[scoffs]
Cabrón.
-The hell are you doing here?
-I could ask you the same thing.
I can't believe you're here, cabrón.
What a fucking mess you two got into.
You actually got El Chapo!
Fucking crazy.
Well, my boy Barraza here,
thanks to him, we got El Cholo.
Well, thanks then.
Any time.
Well, I've got somebody
waiting for me, huh?
[both chuckle]
Go get her, man!
-Sheesh.
-Cabrón.
-Glad you're my partner.
-Me too.
Thank you.
-We're fucking idiots, aren't we?
-Oh, complete idiots.
[both chuckle]
IN JULY 2019, JOAQUÍN GUZMÁN LOERA
WAS SENTENCED TO LIFE PLUS 30 YEARS.
"EL CHOLO" IVÁN GASTÉLUM
WAS EXTRADITED TO THE USA
FOR DRUG TRAFFICKING AND FIREARM CRIMES.
CARMONA WAS PROMOTED
AND COMMENDED.
HE WAS ASSIGNED
TO A SECURITY DETAIL OVERSEAS.
CARMONA AND HIS FAMILY
THEN RETURNED TO MEXICO.
HIS WHEREABOUTS
AND IDENTITY REMAIN CLASSIFIED.
HÉCTOR ROSALES WAS DECORATED
FOR HIS BRAVERY
AND ASSIGNED OVERSEAS WITH CARMONA.
HE DECIDED TO POSTPONE HIS RETIREMENT.
HIS WHEREABOUTS
AND IDENTITY REMAIN CLASSIFIED.
[poignant music continues]
[tense music playing]
[music fades]